# Curriculum Vitae

## Steven Marcel Bißantz

N h

Nordparkstraße 10b, 76829 Landau

+49 1525 3606062

 $\searrow$ 

bissantz@uni-landau.de https://github.com/sbissantz

## DOCTORAL RESEARCH

Measurement & Replicability in The Sciences - A metascientific investigation in the role of measurement when replicating empirical findings

In particular, my research focuses on how (a) modifying validated itembased measurements or (b) the use of unvalidated scales affects the replicability of empirical findings. Despite that, I am interessted in predicting replication success with machine learning models.

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

OCT 202I - PRESENT

RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau **PhD Student, Psychology** 

(PROF. DR. EUNIKE WETZEL)

Mainly, I am involved in meta-science; but I also learn about quantitative methods and teach test theory, diagnostics, and R.

MAY 2019 - JUL 2021

Center of Educational Research Research Assistent, Psychology (ZEPF)

I researched mode effects in performance tests (VERA) using structural equation models and multilevel modeling.

SEP 2016 – APR 2018

University of Mannheim Research Assistent, Sociology (PROF. DR. IRENA KOGAN)

Data analysis, literature research, and the administration of the internet presence in English and German were among my tasks.

SEP 2016 – FEB 2017

University of Mannheim Research Assistent, Sociology

(PROF. DR. FRANK KALTER)

As a tutor, I reviewed the course material content, clarified unanswered questions, and deepened the understanding of my fellow students in complementary teaching sessions.

APR 2015 – JUL 2015

Mannheim Center for European Social Research
Research Assistent, Sociology

(MZES)

After theoretical and practical training, I conducted computer-assisted telephone interviews (CATI).

## **MEMBERSHIPS**

OCT 2022 - PRESENT

Statistical Modeling in Psychology
Associate Member of the DFG Research Training Group

JAN 2022 – PRESENT

RPTU Open Science Commission Member and vice chairman, since 2023

(osc)

# **EDUCATION**

2019-2021 M.A., Social Sciences (1.0)

Department of Social Sciences University of Koblenz-Landau

2018-2019 Survey Statistics

Department of Economics University of Bamberg

2014-2018 **B.A., Sociology** (1.6)

Department of Sociology University of Mannheim

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

**Bißantz, S.** (2021). *elisr*: Exploratory Likert Scaling in R. R package version 0.2.0. https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=elisr

Wagner, I., Loesche, P. & **Bißantz**, **S.** (2021). Low-stakes performance testing in Germany by the VERA assessment: analysis of the mode effects between computer-based testing and paper-pencil testing. European Journal of Psychology of Education. 10.1007/S10212021-00532-6

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2021, 2022 (WS)	Test theory & assessment	(EXERCISE)
2022 (WS)	Data analysis in R	(EXERCISE)
2022, 2023 (SS)	Test theory & asssesment	(SEMINAR)

#### COMPUTER SKILLS

OPERATING SYSTEMS Linux, macOS & Windows
LINUX DISTRIBUTIONS Fedora, openSUSE & Arch
STATISTICAL SOFTWARE R, Stan, Stata & SPSS
MISCELLANEOUS LATEX, Git, Vim & Emacs

Proficiency: Server administrator at our lab "Personality, Psychological Assessment, and Psychological Methods" at the RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau.

# **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

**Metascience** What is the effect of scale modifications on inferences, replicability, and effect-size heterogeneity?

**Bayesian Data Analysis** How to maximize information entropy using Bayesian updating?

**Machine Learning** What are efficient ways to minimize cross-entropy in prediction tasks?